Let us denote the set of parameters by theta
so I am going to come up with some kind of
a performance measure for a specific choice
of theta, so I will call it eta of theta right
so for what does the specific choice of theta
correspond to, suppose my theta is like composed
of theta1 theta2... thetaK so I give you values
for theta1 theta2 theta3... theta K so what
does this correspond to ONE policy when I
say I am looking at a specific value for theta
it corresponds to one policy.
So when I say eta of theta that means I am
evaluating that policy somehow okay so what
is the most natural evaluation measure you
can think of for a policy, expected pay off,
right expected the expected payoff is the
evaluation for the policy so yes I am going
to do I am going to do that there okay, so
what is the expected payoff you know what
the expected payoff is, this is the expected
payoff I will get for taking action a.
This is a probability that I will take action
a when I am selecting actions according to
theta right right so this is a standard notation
I do not know if people are familiar with
this, this means pi is a function that is
parameterized by theta right and whatever
specific value I give for theta will define
what that pi is okay and then this means it
is going to take some other argument okay,
so this is the input to the function okay.
Which is defined by these parameters theta
okay so this is how I, when you put a semicolon
here that means it is parameterized form okay,
so essentially since pi a semicolon theta
means that is the policy defined by the current
settings of parameters theta times the q star
a right because q star a is the true expectation
for taking arm a right and then sum over all
a, I will basically get the expected reward
but if I am having a deterministic policy
that means essentially only one arm I will
take all the other arms of probability 0 then
the payoff will be q star of that arm right
okay, so now once I have this kind of a performance
measure so what do I do is essentially I take
theta.
Right I take theta, I find the gradient of
the performance okay so where the gradient
is taken with respect to theta right so I
look at how the performance changes with changing
theta and I will try to move theta in the
direction of the increase in the performance,
okay. So this is called gradient ascent so
people might have heard about gradient descent
earlier so this is gradient descent, so I
am going up the gradient, right.
If the performance improves if I change theta
in some direction then I will change my theta
in that direction, okay does that make sense
people see this or do you need more pictorial
analogies, so let us say that I have one parameter
theta, I have one parameter theta right and
that is eta of theta, let us say this is my
is this a good way to do it, right let us
say that I have my performance whatever is
an acceptable range of theta so my performance
goes like this right.
So I initially start off with some guess for
theta right that will be my initial guess
for theta right then what I do, I measure
this and then I compute the gradient right
so the gradient is there so if I look at which
direction I should move my theta, essentially
I should move in this direction so I move
a little bit and set that as theta1 okay then
I measure the gradient again okay still I
have to move in this direction more so I keep
doing that and I think I will declare that
I have reached the highest performance there.
So this is essentially how I do it okay there
are a couple of questions which you might
ask me here, why do I have to do this in this
kind of an incremental fashion why cannot
I just take the derivative of that and find
the highest point and settle down there, sorry
I do not have the function at all so forget
about closed form, I do not have the function
at all what is that function that is q star
of a times pi right I know pi but I do not
know q star.
If I know q star my problem is solved right,
I do not need to do any of these things, that
function itself I do not know right. So how
am I evaluating this function and trying to
find the gradient, by sampling so I am pulling
a lot of arms right according to my current
policy pi right and then I am trying to evaluate
the policy pi and then trying to find the
gradient at that point right, so because everything
is done through sampling.
So whatever gradient I compute at this point
will not be the correct gradient right this
is too simple I mean it has to be either that
direction or this direction, this is too simple
right but think of a multi dimensional case
when there are many many parameters, the right
direction you will have to compute can get
messed up right so instead of going in all
the parameters instead of identifying the
right direction some parameters you might
get the right direction some parameters you
will get the wrong direction and so on so
forth right.
Therefore every time you make only small steps
because if we tried if we say oh I have computed
the direction of the gradient I will just
keep moving in that direction until my.. or
I will take a huge step in the direction until
my performance drops or something that would
not work because the direction itself might
be wrong so in this case I mean we have always
moved in the right direction every step.
It is possible that because you are estimating
the gradient you might actually make the wrong
computation and move in the wrong direction
sometimes okay so what really you can hope
for from these kinds of methods which are
called stochastic gradient approaches okay
they are called stochastic gradient approaches
because you do not know the true gradient
and every time you make an estimate of what
the true gradient will be and then you are
using that for making moves.
I mean the most popular form of this will
be called SGD which is stochastic gradient
descent okay it is a very popular optimization
technique nowadays but in this case you are
using stochastic gradient ascent but still
it is the same stochastic gradient idea and
so you have to be careful about how you use
it and the best that you can hope to get is
that in an expected sense over many many updates
right.
I did I did now I showed you two updates so
if you make this update says this kind of
updates many times in an expected sense you
will move in the right direction of the gradient
right so that is the kind of guarantee that
typically you expect for these kinds of methods
okay, so is it clear now is clearer now if
people are not hundred percent clear about
what I am talking just stop and ask right
I can elaborate at the risk of slowing down
yeah.
Good point yeah so we will come to that so
we are going to talk about that, so we do
not know the function itself right how are
you going to estimate the gradient right,
so we will come to that in a minute
so we know we have a functional form for this
now I am going to write down the gradient
for this expression right this is the expression
we have, I am going to write down the gradient
for this expression.
Okay so this is assuming that q star of a
because it is a parameter of the problem right
it has nothing to do with the policy right
as far as your policy parameterization is
concerned q star is a constant right because
it is a it is something to do with the problem
so I can I do not have to do this I just have
to differentiate this with respect to theta
right, so now I am going to do some hand waving.
So what did I do here, I multiplied and divided
by pi, okay.
So for this to work what do I need, pi is
non zero for all a so this is one condition
that you need for all of this any kind of
pi that you assume okay has to be nonzero
for all a it has to assume some nonzero probability,
now if you think about this particular expression
right I will put a bracket around that right
so what does this remind you off, does it
look like an expectation computation I am
looking at the expected value of some function
right.
Where I am taking samples according to probability
pi, right this looks like an expected value
right, I am summing over all possible outcomes
of A all possible values here right that is
the probability so I am essentially taking
the expectation taken according to pi of...
is it fine right. So everybody on board with
that right so that I can write that expectation
oh okay sorry about the font, so the expectation
is taken with respect to pi, okay.
Is it clear? so now we know how to make an
estimate of the expectations right how do
you do that we draw sample and then take an
average right so we can do that so essentially
what I am going to do is pull an arm that
is a sample right when you say draw a sample
according to pi that essentially means I have
to pull an arm and what happens when I pull
an arm, I get a reward right but the reward
does not figure in here.
The expectation of the reward directly figures
in here right so I can actually write this
as a double expectation you know mean the
expectation is taken over not only pi but
also over the process that generates the reward
q star right it is also the process that generates
the reward so my sample here is going to consist
of Rt right is it clear I mean this is a very
subtle thing, people are here with me on this
is it clear.
See q star itself is already an expectation
right so instead of because I do not know
this expectation I will have to estimate this
expectation as well and that can be done by
just taking the Rt so what I will do now is
at every time t I will sample an arm, I will
pull the arm figure out what the reward is
right but is that sufficient, no I have to
do this right I just cannot use the Rt directly
I will have to use this also right.
So I will take the gradient of pi, evaluated
at A divided by the.. so this is my one sample
right this is because the expectation I am
taking is of this quantity so the sample that
I draw is actually this right and I have to
do this over I do not know some number n,
pi a t you are right, is it fine , no no no
I am not using t I am sorry, I promised you
that I will use n for discrete time and t
for continuous time.
So we are talking about discrete times here
it has to be n I do not know if i used t here,
sorry about that but all of you a erase in
your notebook that t and write down n, for
this part of, sorry about that right so this
is clear is there anything missing right,
so I need to have 1 by n there so this gives
me the gradient right so this is fine oh are
we still okay, we are not because this is
actually a estimation okay.
So I cannot put equal to there, it is only
an approximation great so can we compute this,
we can right because we know pi we are the
ones who determine what pi should be right
because at the beginning I choose a parameterized
representation that I can choose whatever
suppose it is softmax well I know how to take
the derivative of soft max right or if it
is a continuous action I can just use a say
a Gaussian right I know how to take the derivative
of a Gaussian with respect to its parameters
right.
Or if it is a multinomial what do I do you
know how to take the derivative of a multinomial
as well right so the derivative is very simple
so I know what form of the function I choose
it so I can go ahead and take the derivative,
there are a couple of reasons for it
so estimating q star need not always be the
right thing to do okay because I have not
introduced all the complications I am hesitating
whether I should go there or not.
But the thing is so the q star function sometimes
turns out to be incredibly complex okay as
a function of the state space okay not necessarily
here right as a function of the state space
q turns out to be incredibly complex whereas
a direct representation of the policy turns
out to be a lot more simple right for example
there are many inventory control problems
where the policy essentially turns out to
be if the inventory is below a certain level
you buy, if the inventory is above a certain
level you do not buy okay.
But then the value function itself becomes
a very complicated function of how many of
the items are left of different types and
so on so forth so the function itself becomes
a lot harder to learn so there are instances
like this where this is easier to learn right
and there are a couple of other cases especially
when you are talking about very large problems
for example we will see that policy gradient
approaches generalize very easily to problems
with continuous actions.
So where there are individual actions so if
you are talking about value function methods
right where I typically store a value for
each action now I am going to have continuous
actions it is not clear how to handle it there
are ways of handling it but it turns out that
they are not that well behaved as policy gradient
approaches are when the action space is continuous
right so there are many reasons why you want
to consider continuous actions I mean policy
gradient methods.
Primarily I would say the, one of the primary
motivations is to handle continuous actions,
okay. So this is some kind of a batch update,
hmm because the expectation is taken with
respect to the pi, yeah you could do more
simplifications of that if you want to right
but what is your question again, yeah but
I need to take this expectation with respect
to the sample the probability distribution
pi right.
So and I cannot separate this I cannot write
this out as some I really cannot simplify
this further because my q star is here right
so this is the expectation of this whole quantity
so I really cannot split this apart and say
that okay I will just simplify this expectation
and take only the expected value of q star
a, can I, I cannot take E of AB is not A into
E of B is it if A is only a constant right
not otherwise I am not sure whether we can
simplify this further right.
So what we are doing here is some kind of
a batch mode so if you think of how we are
doing this sampling so I am taking some theta
fixing it pulling the arms multiple times
right fixing theta pulling arms capital n
times and then taking this average right and
then what computing the gradient and then
using that to change the parameters right
this is one way of doing it another way of
doing it to say that okay I will have a theta
I will pull an arm I will compute the gradient.
And I will change the parameters right so
you can have a some kind of an incremental
version.
So where I am saying at every step I will
change my parameters by some fraction delta
t, I will do this at every step right sorry
and so this is what I am doing so what I am
essentially will end up doing is theta will
be theta plus delta theta, theta n +1 will
be theta n plus delta theta n right I will
do this
at every time, every time I pull an arm I
will change this right I mean that is essentially
the gradient of the ln it turns out this simplifies
your life a lot this observation simplifies
your life a lot when you are trying to actually
solve the solve problems later right now you
can immediately think of soft max becoming
very easy to differentiate we have now taken
log and there is lots of exponents there right.
So all the e power thing will vanish so it
will become lot easier to differentiate for
you right so what I am going to do now is
to include another term here rather arbitrarily
called bn which we refer to as the reinforcement
baseline, right and adding the bn should not
affect the whole process that is what the
bn should not really be a function of a, yeah
theta basically so it should not be a function
of the action I take right.
If it is a function of the action I take then
it becomes dependent on theta so as long as
it is not a function of the action I take
I can keep adding a I can add this thing it
is called the reinforcement baseline right
so one way of thinking about it is I am when
I get a reward right I do not know if the
reward is a good reward or a bad reward so
giving a baseline and saying that if you are
above this baseline it is a good reward if
you are below this baseline it is a bad reward
okay.
kind of allows you to calibrate the rewards
right one typical way in which this reinforcement
base line is used is to just take the average
of all the rewards I have obtained so far
right this is all the rewards regardless of
which arm I play I keep accumulating the rewards
right now when I play a particular arm if
it is above this average then it is a good
arm if it is below this average then it is
a bad arm right.
So valid after, yeah..hmm fine.. eventually
it will eventually it will be all fine right
so initially you might be making some mistakes
because the initial few the b will be wrong
right so you might actually think a good arm
is bad and a bad arm is good I mean depending
but eventually it will all work out does not
matter right so if you think about if the
reward is good right then I will go in the
direction of the gradient right but if the
reward is bad then I will go in the opposite
direction of the gradient right.
So in some sense that is a little waving here
that but then it is fine it turns out that
adding the reinforcement baseline makes the
convergence behavior of this algorithm a little
more stable okay but it is not necessary you
can if you are going to implement this you
can do it without the reinforcement baseline
also right so this is called the
and this term is sometimes called the
called the characteristic eligibility.
So what is the characteristic eligibility
it essentially tells you, if you
do that then you get into actor critic I will
talk about that later, I will talk about that
later yeah sure yeah you could do that right
and that is essentially one of the motivations
for getting into actor critic algorithms,
so that requires you to maintain q star estimates
as well as the pi estimates as well as the
pi representation.
So the pi would be the critic and the q star
would be the actor,uff.. other way around
the pi would be the actor the q star will
be the critic so that is another class of
algorithms right which address some of the
drawbacks of policy gradient approaches right
I will talk about it but somewhere halfway
down the course not now so after this I am
going to go back and start talking about the
full RL problem and at some point I will come
back and do actor critic yeah.
So his question was why do I use Rn right
why cannot I plug-in q there right you could
and yeah and typically when you do that it
performs better the algorithm it is actually
a it reduces variants significantly at the
cost of adding significant bias right there
are other issues you know you well you know
what are the other issues going to actor critic
but I will talk about it later right and going
back.
So why is that called the characteristic eligibility
so if you think about it so it essentially
chooses which of the thetas are most responsible
for a change at that point right so that is
the term that determines that is the term
that is the theta dependent term in your updates
right and it tells you which theta is more
responsible for change that is happening here
there suppose there are three or four different
parameters that I have right.
So whichever has the highest gradient whichever
direction you have the highest gradient that
is the direction where the largest change
is going to happen right, so it is essentially
this telling you which theta is more eligible
to receive the update that is why it is called
the characteristic eligibility right did that
make sense to people I think i have lost more
people today than in the previous classes
no great.
So this whole thing right this way of doing
this incremental version of doing this update
is actually called the called the reinforce
algorithm, first proposed by this guy called
Williams in 98, Williams proposed reinforce
in I think in 1988 and in fact he proposed
this in the context of neural networks right
so he when he came up with this algorithm
neural networks were still ruling right.
So he proposed this in the context of neural
networks he said that your thetas are weights
of a neural network right and then he came
up with this update and then the biggest contribution
he did was he said that hey this looks like
a really crazy update right I mean how is
this going to work and initially people are
very skeptical he actually showed that in
an expected sense right even though I am doing
this update after just pulling one arm in
an expected sense the gradient will be in
the right direction right.
If I repeat this experiment multiple times
and I watch how the weights evolve right they
will actually move in the same direction as
it would have happened if I had computed the
correct gradient and then taken steps in that
direction so essentially he established that
for this reinforce update and it since then
it has kind of been the one sole hope of convergence
for all kinds of complex function approximations
and RL okay.
So it works really well but it is extreme
extremely slow, reinforce is extremely slow
because the variance is very high so when
I want to move on from this I will talk about
the other problems of reinforce here is a
horrible part about the paper so reinforce
is actually an acronym there is an expansion
each letter stands actually for a word he
came up with a name for the algorithm which
actually shortened to reinforce.
And then that started the trend for convoluted
names in the RL community okay anyone knows
what the expansion of reinforce is do you
know what the expansion of reinforce is, forgot
okay, I cannot for the life of me I refuse
to memorize what reinforce stands for, great
so let us do some special cases of reinforce
right I want to consider a binary bandit.
Or let us say I take a bandit with two actions
okay but they can have arbitrary rewards okay
here is the parameterization I choose this
is essentially the Bernoulli thing right so
I have two actions with some probability theta
I will select action 1,1-theta I will select
action 0 okay so what do I need to do now
to get that update rule we have to find doe
ln pi by doe theta so what this will be, it
will be 1 if a is 1, it will be minus 1 if
correct.
No!! yeah look at ln pi right it is not doe
pi by doe theta, it is doe ln pi by doe theta
yeah so it will be 1 by theta if a is one
and it will be minus 1 by 1 minus theta if
a is zero right, we can write it like that,
substitute a is 1, so 1 minus theta and 1
minus theta will get cancelled out you will
get 1 by theta. Substitute a is zero, theta
and theta will get cancelled out, you will
get minus 1 by 1 minus theta okay a very compact
way of writing it and now I am going to say
that I will choose my alpha to be some rho
times
theta into 1 minus theta.
So it turns out that as long as your alpha
is not dependent on the actual reward that
you get okay it can be dependent on the theta
this is what William showed as long is not
dependent on the actual reward you are all
fine okay you will converge so that is essentially
this is result so I can make it dependent
on my theta it should not be dependent on
the actual action you sample okay and the
actual reward that you receive so as long
as that is there it is fine all right.
And I am going to choose my b to be 0, why
am I making this specific choices so now I
let me plug everything back in so what does
my delta theta look like, so alpha n which
is rho into theta into 1 minus theta into
Rn minus bn which is 0 so it is Rn into doe
ln this which will be a minus theta by theta
into 1 minus theta right so what do I end
up getting rho okay so what is the what is
the interpretation for this, let us say I
take action one okay and I get a reward of
1.
So what do I get, rho into 1 minus theta that
is how much I change my value by so which
is essentially this right rho into 1 minus
theta right suppose I took action but what
about I took action one right and my reward
was one right what will I do for 0 oh there
is no there is only one parameter right it
is automatically my other parameter will get
adjusted because it is 1 minus theta suppose
I took action one and got a reward of 0 what
happens no change.
Suppose I took action of 0 and got a reward
of 1 what happens, minus theta into Rn right
so that is essentially what I have here right
so this is minus theta into Rn right so theta
is my pi t a t if you remember right and then
this R so that is essentially what I have,
so this is this is what L R-I right so essentially
L R-I is a is a gradient following algorithm
actually it is a reinforce algorithm right
so you can try to look at different choices
for the alphas and the different choices for
pi right and try to come up with this kind
of update rules right.
We will do the soft max action selection as
I described in the previous class right so
do that right where I replace all my qs with
some arbitrary theta suppose I have K actions
or K arms then I will have theta1 to theta
K these are my parameters and the probability
of selecting arm I will be e power theta I
by beta divided by summation over j e power
theta j by beta right so this is my softmax
expression so derive my reinforce update rules
assuming that is the expression, right that
is one I am going to give you another homework.
The same thing, I said one of the nice things
about doing reinforce.
Is that it allows us to handle continuous
actions right allows us to handle continuous
actions, actions need not be discrete so far
we have been looking at the cases where actions
are discrete so I am going to use, that as
my probability distribution that is my policy
okay give me the reinforce update rules so
how many rules will I have for reinforce update
rules here 2 - one for the mu, one for the
sigma right.
Get me the reinforce update rules and yeah
so try to simplify as much as possible because
when you do the ln mu, I mean the ln pi derivatives
will get all kinds of weird constants coming
there so you can choose your alpha appropriately
so that some of these constants get cancelled
out so that I can have just like we did here
right I chose my rho to be theta into 1 minus
theta likewise you can choose your constants
in this case also right the alphas to be something
different so that you end up with a good nice-looking
form okay great.
IIT Madras Production
Funded by
Department of Higher Education
Ministry of Human Resource Development
Government of India
www.nptel.ac.in
Copyrights Reserved